<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands warning, that is three remarkable visions of Stephen Melish, an inhabitant of Breslaw, the chief city of Silesia Englished in the year 1664.</title>
            <author>Melish, Stephen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11164735</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11164735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1426:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands warning, that is three remarkable visions of Stephen Melish, an inhabitant of Breslaw, the chief city of Silesia Englished in the year 1664.</title>
                  <author>Melish, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title reads: Englands warning, that is, the 115th vision of Stephen Melish, June the 15th, 1664.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mystics --  Germany.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Prophecies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Englands Warning: That is, Three Remarkable VISIONS OF Stephen Meliſh, An Inhabitant of <hi>Breſlaw,</hi> the chief City in <hi>Sileſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſhed in the Year, 1664.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46473:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IF the Rule where to try Prophets by, given by God himſelf <hi>(Deut. 18.21)</hi> is ſtill in force, then no doubt but <hi>Stephen Meliſh</hi> hath not brought forth his Propheſies by the will of man, but as it is written; <hi>Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is evident accordingly, as to the matter of the fact, that very many of thoſe Prophecies of the ſaid <hi>Meliſh</hi> have been fulfilled in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> and thereabouts, as he, that may confer with them the things paſt afterwards, will not deny. See the Annotations to each one of his Viſions, printed beyond Seas in the Latin and in the German tongue.</p>
            <p>Why would then any body detract them Divine Authtrity, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be bound to reſpect them as the Counſel of the Lord of Hoſts, ſent unto thoſe that are concerned in it, as to the end of their Preſervation and Welfare?</p>
            <p>Therefore, if, like as the Counſel and Secreſie of Kings and Princes ſhall be kept in ſilence; ſo on the contrary the Work of God muſt be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, revealed or made manifeſt: The duty of every one that fearth the Lord, requires of him to do accordingly, and not to keep, from thoſe at the leaſt that are concerned, any Counſel of him, who <hi>doth nothing but he revealeth his Secrets unto his Servants the Prophets,</hi> to wit, the Lord God, <hi>Amos 3.7.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46473:2"/>
               <head>ENGLAND'S WARNING; <hi>That is, the 115th</hi> VISION <hi>of</hi> Stephen Meliſh, <hi>June the 15th.</hi> 1664.</head>
               <p>THis night I had a wonderful Viſion, but I do not know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I was aſleep or awake: I was brought out of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs into the City, in broad day-light; but as ſoon as I was entered into it, there it was night preſently, and there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared an horrible ſight in the Sky towards the Eaſt: And ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I knew not who, ſaid unto me, <hi>Where are now thoſe Incredulous? let them come forth and look upon the wonderful things of God, what they may portend.</hi> And as ſoon as he was yet a ſpeaking, there came out of the Stars ſome bloody Rods, like unto Brooms; their handle tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downward, and the points upward, flames and ſparks of fire ſparkling forth of them; and he ſaid unto me, <hi>Let the Burgomaſters and Aldermen, with other chief men, and the Citizens, or at leaſt ſome of thy Friends, be called for, to be Witneſſes.</hi> But with all my bauling and loud crying, I could make no body to ſtir, except the Watchmen of the City, that were walking hither and thither tremblingly. Then I came to ſtand in the Market-place, and went on with a moſt clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous voice, to cry what I could; for he commanded me, <hi>Cry aloud for a Witneſs againſt them, or write it:</hi> But I had nothing where to write upon, and it was exceeding dark, and all were aſleep every-where.</p>
               <p>Then he hat ſpoke to me like a man (but I could not know him by his countenance, nor by his ſpeech, yet I ſaw him) commanded the Drums to be beaten. But all the noiſe of the Drums could make no body awake. <hi>Let the Trumpets be ſounded forth,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>both through the Streets, and upon the Towers;</hi> but all was in vain. Then I ſaw that <hi>fiery Rod</hi> (ſtanding in the Eaſt, juſt where the Sun riſes in this month) turned into fire, and two other Fires, on both ſides, aſcending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the midſt of the Sky; Woods, Villages and Cities being kindled by them, no body appearing or ſtirring to quench that Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or to remove any thing of theirs out of it, or at the leaſt to ſave themſelves by flight. I ſeeing all this with horror, began to quake
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46473:3"/>and tremble the more, becauſe I knew not what would become of all that: But the man ſaid to me, <hi>As for thee, fall not into a fright; fear God, and admoniſh thy houſe of Repentance daily, for to eſcape what ſhall come ſwiftly.</hi> But I asked him: Sir, when is ſuch a thing to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us? Tell me, and I'll tell to others. Anſwer was returned; <hi>Thou alſo, haſt thou forgot that great Prodigy (on the Sun) that hath been ſeen through all Chriſtendom, and beyond? And likewiſe of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prodigious Signs over ſo many Lands, Cities, Villages, Towns, that have been ſeen ſo often, to the end all ſhould be left without excuſe. That on the Sun did happen ten years ago, when from the ninth hour till beyond mid-day the Sun was taken over with darkneſs, and recovered his light, from the Eaſt Weſtward, like unto a Sickle. For lo,</hi> 1. <hi>The Sickle from the Eaſt is coming to mow down the moyety of Chriſtians of the whole Europe, betwixt the South and the West.</hi> 2. <hi>But afterwards he ſhall become a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker alſo of that Sun-light.</hi> 3. <hi>The Rod of the Eaſt ſhall ſtrike both Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Impious; yet theſe unto destruction, and thoſe for a tryal. The Fires thou hast ſeen, are the Plagues of the angry God, whom no body can withſtand, nor eſcape thoſe Plagues. The Darkneſs, and deep dead-ſleep, ſignifies their uttermoſt ſecurity, which men of this day are fallen into, like unto</hi> Pharoah; <hi>the more God threatneth with puniſhment, and ſheweth his ſcourges, the more they become obſtinate, mocking at all things. The Kings and Princes are aſleep, the Magiſtrates are aſleep, all the People without and within the City are aſleep, being altogether very ſecure in their ſins; and ſaying, Such-like Signs have alſo been of old, ſo they are now, and will be after us too. But hearken to what I ſay: The Miracles are the Word of God, and the daily Obtestations of his Puniſhments. Thy Voice are the true Miniſters of the Churches, and their Writs, that do denounce the terrible Judgments of God.</hi> 4. <hi>The Drums and Trumpets are the Wars, that now begin of the one againſt the other, to the end all might be left without excuſe. Now the eleventh hour is come, and the twelfth hour too, in which the Lord will pour forth his Anger upon the Apoſtates from the Truth, and upon the Impious</hi> Pharoahs, <hi>thoſe cruel Rackers both of the Bodies and Souls, that kill with the Sword, and with the venemous Doctrine of Satan together; and upon all that fear men more than God; and upon the Secular Power, that abuſeth the Sword (given unto protection of the good ones) to root out the Church, and to revenge themſelves to their own ends: and upon all unjuſt partial Judges, looking for Money, and ſetting aſide their Conſciences; And upon all Simoniacous,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46473:3"/>Luxurious, Sluggiſh Prieſts; and upon the whole Multitude, both in the City and in the Countries, given over to Treachery, Betraying, Murder, Robbery, Pride, Gluttony, wherewith they ſhorten their lives themſelves.</hi> And ſo I, being admoniſhed of all this, was not to keep ſilence any longer, but to write this, and to publiſh it.</p>
               <p>After this I came to my ſelf again, and the Clock ſtruck <hi>One,</hi> and ſoon after it ſtruck <hi>Two,</hi> (or the ſecond hour) and preſently it waxed day. This makes me to conceive a good hope, that God, after a ſharp chaſtiſement will ſhorten the time, and make out of the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hour but one. All the day before, I was very much troubled, as not knowing how it was with me, as if ſome evil would befal me: Yet I did recommend my ſelf to the Lord, and fell aſleep, from the eighth hour until the tenth; from thence I counted all the hours fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, even as being not aſleep, but awake; feeling all my ſenſes as lively as any man out of ſleep can do, ſeeing and hearing all. And therefore I aroſe, walk'd up and down in the Chamber, and cryed thus ſhrilly, that my folk did hear me, yet not knowing what it ſignified. So then this my Dream (in caſe it was a Dream) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from the <hi>eighth</hi> to the <hi>ſecond</hi> hour.</p>
               <p>As concerning that Eclipſe of the Sun (in the year 1654. <hi>Aug.</hi> 12) and its natural conſtitution or reaſon, I confeſs my ſelf to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant therein, not knowing any thing of it. But the man ſaid expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>The tenth hour was paſt already, and the eleventh was approaching:</hi> Yet theſe two laſt ſhould paſs away quickly, that ſo the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs may receive again <hi>his ſhining.</hi> The Lord God Almighty help to it for his Mercy-ſake.</p>
               <p>And this is now that remarkable Viſion, which I, according to Commandment, forthwith have written down, and ſend unto thee, dear Friend of God, to the end that thou mayeſt make it known, and not to hide it from any that fear the Lord, to ſtir up, if it might ſtill be, any that would awaken out of the ſleep of ſin, leſt the fault fall upon us. He that will receive our Admonition, let him receive it; he that will deſpiſe it, let him deſpiſe it, <hi>viz.</hi> them that are wiſe and juſt by themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The 116th</hi> VISION, <hi>June</hi> 20. 1664.</head>
               <p>As concerning that Fiery Rod, together with the twofold Collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fire, I ſaw, that it moved from the Eaſt through the South, into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46473:4"/>the Weſt, from whence did ariſe an exceeding thick ſmoak, rouling as it were, into the North; whence aroſe an exceeding great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the Nations. They fell ſo fiercely incenſed one againſt another, that it was a terror to look upon them: they dealt not one with another like Chriſtians, but like as wild barbarous Nations, bended upon mutual deſtruction: yet I knew not what Nations they were, becauſe they were not named, and by their ſpeech or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage I could not diſcern them. This onely I aſſuredly know and write, that the ſaid Fire did ſtay in the Weſt, and ſtill it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding dark every where, which made the Fire grow hotter and hotter, even as if the whole World ſhould be inflamed: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, men were aſleep very deeply, and no body any more was to awake them; and although ſome did awake as it were, <hi>and looked upon that fire in the Weſt, yet they took no notice of it,</hi> becauſe they all had drunk of the Cup of Malignity, Enviouſneſs, Fury, and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſtineſs, whereof they were made ſo drunk, that there was no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, in what Clamour, ſound of Trumphets, and noiſe of Drums ſoever, that could make them awake to conſider the iſſue of all ſuch doings, in caſe no body would give over and leave off Perſecution and diſpatching of others. After, I heard Lamentations of ſuch as were grieved, for that they had drunken out of the Cup of the <hi>Eſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiſh Dragon,</hi> whereof the Land was thus deſolated, the King thruſt out, the People deſtroyed, the Lords and Pillars of the Land fallen down, the <hi>Pious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>achers killed or baniſhed,</hi> the Children ſcattered throughout the ſtreets, there they lay, and none was that did help it; never ſuch a VVar hath been <hi>like unto this in the Weſt.</hi> O would to God the King might be awake, and take Counſel to prevent this ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt deſtroying Burning and Inflamation!</p>
               <p>Above that, I have ſeen one of the Northern Kings, eſpecially the King in <hi>Denmark,</hi> ſtanding in the Flame, as it were ſcorched, who will be thruſt alſo cut of his Kingdome, and his Cities with the key of the Sea (the <hi>Sound</hi>) fall into the power of the VVeſtern Part, unleſs he look to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe that black Smoak will ſpread forth its ſparks of Fire in the North too; but the North VVind will ſoon ſcatter them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y may be quenched; for the <hi>Eſauvitiſh</hi> contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhortly be manifeſted, therefore let them well look about, and not permit that the Southern and VVeſtern oppreſs their Neighbours betwixt the VVeſt and North; for when the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46473:4"/>(though they have bound themſelves a rod upon their back) ſhould be oppreſſed, then the Northern alſo will have buſineſs enough.</p>
               <p>VVould to God that I might be found a Liar in foretelling theſe Plagues to the World, which the Lord of Heaven hath been pleaſed to manifeſt, not only by the Scriptures, and ſo many Prophets raiſed up, and other Pious men, but alſo by <hi>me,</hi> poor little one; yea by ſo many Signes in the Skie, Earth, Sea, given forth to forewarn us: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was conſtrained thereto, yet I believe, and am reſolved to dye upon it, that God ſpeaketh truth, and is faithful to what he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, and a Revenger of wickedneſs; yea, becauſe he is merciful alſo, his Mercy ſlows from him before the execution: The like is to be ſeen in <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Jonah.</hi> But this it is, there be many that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtiff necks and uncircumciſed hearts, will rather hear and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the counſel of the Devil, or Deviliſh counſels, than the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God; and no other counſel there is left then to caſt our ſelves in the bottomleſs pit of the Mercy of God, for to eſcape the Flame of the Anger of God, who even now goeth about to conſume the world with Sword and Peſtilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The 117th VISION, <hi>June</hi> 26. 64.</head>
               <p>After I had paſſed three dayes with Prayers and Sighs unto God, in conſideration of the approaching of ſo great an Anger, Beſeeching him he would turn from his Anger, and grant his People before the worlds end, a friendly Peace. I fell of a ſudden in a heavy diſeaſe of the body, but in far greater anguiſh of my ſoul, inſomuch that I was crying aloud, <hi>Will the Lord caſt off for ever, and will he be favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble no more? Hath God forgotten to be gratious? Hath he in anger ſhut up his tender Mercies?</hi> and the inward diſtreſſes of my ſoul was ſo exceeding horrid, that there was left no comfort in the leaſt: And this laſted a whole day, inſomuch that I knew not on what ſide to turn me, being as a man left deſtitute of all kind of Patience. Then the Devil came too and tempted me, endeavouring to quench that ſmall confidence alſo, that I might have left in me towards God. My Mother, my Wife, my Children, they <hi>all ſtood</hi> round about me aſtoniſhed, and weeping, no counſel nor conſolation they could give me, and I looking upon them was therewith the more afflicted,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46473:5"/>ſeeing I muſt be gone and leave them in beggarlineſs; for there was nothing but very Death to be expected. They overcharging me, with that I had not diſpoſed of my houſe, nor put in order the leaſt thing. In few words, the tormenting pain of my ſoul did ſo increaſe, that I fell to roar like a Lion, clamouring with a great voice, ſaid: <hi>On your knees, and cry unto the Lord, that he ſuccour me.</hi> By and by my anguiſhed Soul felt ſome eaſe; and ſo I lay there, like an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied wreſtler, as wet as ſwimming in the water, until the fifth hour after noon. The next morning I found my ſelf much better, nevertheleſs feeling throughout all the veins and bones of my right hand and ſide of the whole body ſenſible ſmarts, untill the fifth day; then being aſleep, an ancient Man came to me, by me never ſeen before nor known, and ſpake to me very comfortably, <hi>Thy Dolours Anguiſh and tormenting Pains within and without, ſignifie the Dolours of the People of God, that are now at hand: Be thou not aſtoniſhed at the repreſentation of ſuch within thee by the Lord of Heaven, who now ſhall aſſault and invade the whole World becauſe of the ſins of men; and of their intolerable Pride and Forgetfulneſs of God; for their ſins have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended the Clouds and cry for revenge: And the Lord looking down ſees but very few that repent, therefore ſuch Plagues are a coming upon them, that they will clamour like as thou haſt clamoured. And thou haſt well done, that thou haſt not yeelded unto ſuch Temptations: Give the Glory and Praiſe to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To all Chriſtians I therefore do appeal, having felt in me ſuch unſpeakable pain, praying them all with what humbleneſs ſoever I can; And again, I intreat you, yea, I intreat you a third time by the Lord God; by our precious Redemption, by the Bloodſhed of Jeſus Chriſt, and by the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt that every day we are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of; and by that out-poured Love, crying in our hearts with unſpeakable ſighs, <hi>Abba, Father;</hi> and by the Mercifulneſs given to you from the Lord, and by your Conjugal-Love betwixt Man and Wife, and by the Fatherly Love betwixt Father, Mother and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and by all thoſe Benefits given unto you and yours every day, for your Livelihood, for the Conſervation of your Cities and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ye are Inhabitants of, to the end, to ſerve the Lord the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant of Heaven, I beſeech you once more to the uttermoſt; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> and be converted to the Lord at this very inſtant, leſt it may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46473:5"/>be too late after thoſe evils are already come. Prevent thoſe evils, I requeſt you, that are a rouling towards you, leſt a late diſlike or regret (I ſee at a diſtance) come ſuddenly upon you, becauſe ye have hearkened unto the Voice of the helliſh Dragon and his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
               <p>O <hi>England!</hi> remember how thou art diſtracted within thy ſelf, more inclined to thy uttermoſt Deſtruction rather than Conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore I, the moſt little worm of all, beſeech you, firſt, the Weſtern King, that he deſiſt to hear the Voice of the ſaid Dragon, and his Officers; let him rather hear the Voice of God: let him deſiſt from Proviſion of War, to deſtroy Cities, and Peoples, and Commonwealths; and to ſhed that Chriſtian blood, which hath been redeemed by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt. In caſe he will do ſo, and let the War alone, it ſhall be fulfilled, that which I have written and ſtill write, That the Lord Jeſus will enlarge him great Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which he ſhall obtain and ſee very ſhortly. Alſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I entreat and obteſt, by the Lord God, all wiſe Counſellors, and thoſe of Love-burning-Lamps of the People of God, even as being the Pillars and Workmen of God's Houſe, to conſider of what evil muſt follow in caſe no body takes care to quench this horrid (by it ſelf) unquenchable Fire; And how it cannot be extinguiſhed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by the mercifulneſs of God, that can be obtained, when we turn to ſerious Repentance, and growing together again in mutual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Is it not the Devil's work, who by us (in <hi>Germany</hi>) hath kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled a Fire, whereunto we have brought the Wood, and poured up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it the Oyl of our Sins? Let it then be your Example, and make haſte to prevent your Evil by Repentance.</p>
               <p>O ye Wiſe and Diſcreet Ones, weigh diligently how this Fire by us hath been kindled, by <hi>thoſe Black Four-cornereds,</hi> who ſeeing they muſt fall here, endeavour to prepare themſelves a Retreat and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in ſome other place, (as prudent ſons of the world) <hi>viz.</hi> in the Weſtern parts, by God's permiſſion: for they ſay, Neither ſhall we be there very ſafe. Yet what ſhall we do? We will put into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Diſorder the Nations, and make them buſtle one againſt another, to overthrow and deſtroy themſelves mutually, that <hi>after they have rooted out themſelves, we may overſow all with our ſeed.</hi> O ſtrange! how great is the craftineſs, how great is the grudg-bearing malignity of that Dragon! and how great is our blindneſs, that we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46473:6"/>have not taken heed, how that by his contrivances ſo many Pillars of the Church have been overthrown, ſo many prudent Judges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and turned out, and there is no end of turning out ſtill: For juſt now they endeavour to bring to paſs, that you Stateſmen, Merchants, Tradeſmen, and the poor plain Country-folk betwixt your ſelves, and with your neighbours, that bring you ſuſtenance, and whatſoever is needful and neceſſary for your uſe and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might fall out with one another, into a mutual ſlaughter and overthrow, to waſte and ruine your own Land and Country.</p>
               <p>But this is not all: They work alſo, that the Kings of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood might joyn battel, eſpecially thoſe towards the North, whither that <hi>black Smoke</hi> went, carrying along with him fire-ſparks of a new Inflamation. Ah! beware, O ye chief Powers and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, ye Kings and Princes! Think, what will remain after the Fire is gone, but Aſhes and Duſt? Ah! will ye not check that riſing Fire, thus exceeding great, that it is like to chaſe all throughout whole <hi>Europe,</hi> and to inflame every-where?</p>
               <p>By the Mercifulneſs of God, once more, I beſeech you; and by the ſafety both of you and yours, be moved with Compaſſion towards your little Children, that cannot as yet diſcern between their right hand and their left, that at the leaſt they might be ſaved. Look how that boyling Sea of the Wicked One's, belching out dirt and mire, doth feel its undoing, by the approaching Anger of God, and the Dragon ſees that his time will be ſhort. Remember the words of Chriſt our Lord, that when Nation ſhall ariſe againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Kingdom againſt Kingdom, then Doomſday draws near; and what at that time we are commanded to do, <hi>viz.</hi> that we ſhall lift up our heads, to look upon the Work of God. Look there how thoſe <hi>Black Four-cornered</hi> run up and down! for their Conſcience is awakened like as a waving Sea. Let them have no place by you, nor their perſons and their ſuggeſtions neither. In caſe ye will not hear this Counſel, then Anguiſh and Dolours will oppreſs you; after which, time of repentance, nor Patience, nor hope of the Grace of God you ſhall have any more; but a burning fire of the Anger of God, that ye now refuſe to avoid, ſhall conſume you. But O that I could perſwade you to prevent it! nay, I ſigh, that the Mercifulneſs of God may prevent you. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46473:6"/>
               <p>For as concerning me, I had no reſt within me until I had written this, leſt the fault fall upon my back, like as upon <hi>Jonah,</hi> unwilling to be obedient unto God. Stedfaſtly I pray, that unto thee, O Gods People, might be given the Grace of <hi>Repentance,</hi> to prevent the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God, by returning to a true Regret and mutual Love. Alas, more Signs and Prodigies ſhall very ſhortly ſhew unto you God's Anger, that is kindling the World with all kind of Plagues. To you that have begun to prevent the ſaid Anger of God, <hi>Be conſtant in your purpoſe:</hi> Faithful is the Lord who hath promiſed: Heaven and Earth will paſs away ſooner than his VVord. And although that Fire flameth already over you, and Anguiſhes and Dolours have ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you at this very time; yet now turn out from that malignant Dragon, the LORD is by the way to ſuccour you.</p>
               <p>And I teſtifie, that notice hath been given unto you, that the LORD hath already let in a ſtormy Wind into the Red <hi>Eſauvitiſh Sea,</hi> inſomuch, that now they are diſquiet in their Conſcience, and ſee, that their abiding here will not be very long more, and the time is at hand, that all who know them, or ſee them, ſhall either betray or kill them.</p>
               <p>However alas! the Chief Powers have been warned enough, <hi>that the Sword hath not been given unto them, to kill, but to defend God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> Yet they alwayes have ſhewed themſelves to be dumb and deaf. Now the Evil comes that is appointed for them: they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to eſcape and prevent it, and will by force put the cauſe of it upon thoſe of ours moſt ſubtilly, according to the Dragon's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and inſpiration.</p>
               <p>All Wars are of the Devil's counſel, and blown up by thoſe <hi>Eſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiſh crafts;</hi> yea, this <hi>Turkiſh War</hi> too; and ſo, that ſame now ſhall begin in the Weſt, to ſhed blood and waſte the Land. Take for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>Hungaria,</hi> where they have begun a Reformation with force, whatſoever might become of it, and they matter not if the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhould become Tributary to the <hi>Turk,</hi> let them but obtain what they aim at, <hi>viz.</hi> the Deſtruction of the Religion. But alas, ye are afar off, the Lord from Heaven will never permit you to root out his People, rather will he ſtir up a wild Nation, that ſhall waſte all with Sword and Fire.</p>
               <p>Tell the King in <hi>ENGLAND</hi> how wiſely the <hi>HOLLANDERS</hi> have begun to act their Cauſe againſt him! having deliberated about
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46473:7"/>compaſſing their Deſign, to fall down at the Feet of the LORD ALMIGHTY, and to put their hope in the Center of his Merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, rather than in their Strength. Therefore however they are to be chaſtized, like as true Sons of <hi>David,</hi> yet they ſhall not ſcape <hi>Scot. free,</hi> that multiply their Scourges againſt the Chaſtened of the Lord. Moreover, let him weigh diligently (the <hi>Englander</hi>) that he is not in vain joyned in Alliance with <hi>Portugal,</hi> but to help him, as being brought under by force, Yet in time to come a glorious Realm, to recover and ſettle their antient Liberties, like as alſo in other Realms. But would to God that the Realms of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Polonia</hi> had accepted of the Peace proffered unto them by the <hi>Turks,</hi> they would not have been caſt into the fire they burn in now. But ſo it happeneth, where Pride bears the Rule, and fulneſs of bread, that from thence ariſeth great ſins and deviliſh contrivances, with perſecutions: Therefore it muſt be accompliſhed: <hi>With what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ye mete, it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi> Thoſe wild Nations muſt make a Hurliburly, to take puniſhment of ſuch as would not acknowledge the day of their Viſitation: The Ruine and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Land is and will come. They would aboliſh the Word of God, but they ſhall be aboliſhed themſelves, yea even now it is upon them.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49, <hi>v.</hi> 11 to 18.</bibl>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
